uh happy
earth day and those of you who have
your guinea practice it's also uh
[Music]
them okay all right so anyway it's a
good day
here we go we're going to start at shea
land
[Music]
yeah don't forget where we are
we start talking fast in the early
morning it's the coffee
uh right so anyway i'll slow down
[Music]
with a cafe explaining
okay so we were talking about uh
the idea of sambara to wake you up for
fifty dollars
who can tell me um
what close oh good yeah
some butter to carry very much but it's
the word for
the
[Music]
uh so i got to think about that
anyway the two collections uh
pure good karma that we need to make
[Music]
and it doesn't mean accumulate more
numbers of good deeds or something
like if you
so he says please remember
when we're talking about buddhas or what
creates buddhas
don't forget some compasses embrace
embrace what here's the answer
[Music]
of something if you don't have bodhisana
merit yeah okay
[Music]
there's a normal kind of collection of
good karma
in terms of embracing perfection
you know normal people can pile up karma
and we can call it some butter
[Music]
the point is what separates
uh even
okay so techniques
yeah is that they are better at soaking
collecting okay and collecting all right
now uh he's talking about even in the
desire realm
in their final birth um
[Music]
in their final rebirth and they say in
the desire room
they don't need other teachers okay and
the minutes
[Music]
everyone says i don't need a teacher i'm
this one
i'm this guy you know i don't need a
teacher i know everything
that's
[Music]
done
who can pretty much get to enlightenment
uh
they got really close in their last life
and then they fell in front of a truck
okay
it's not like that i mean you feel like
it should be like that right
it's not like that it's that you know
okay
almost immediately but they died
they can work more in this life or
something like that it's not really like
that
it's that they were about to reach
nirvana and something happened
and then in this life there's no choice
they have to reach nervous
[Music]
what's what's what sutra is that
now
and that's why we say they don't need
a teacher in the next life it's not that
they somehow teach themselves
it's not that they are super smart which
is what people think when they hear they
don't need a teacher
it's that they just died accidentally
[Music]
um
looks like a buddha head or something
that's called wrong and it says
okay
i couldn't find a cave that didn't have
snakes and
coyotes
[Music]
and i said that's that's it
these buddhas are self-made buddhas
okay the sanskrit is solitary buddha
the tibetan is self buddha
and self means self
made okay
and that comes from this sentence he
says
[Music]
self-made wisdom is very important
by the way i have a picture power wow
wow
of a lady making a pot
yeah i i just feel like she's
right okay
and it's a nice idea of i just had this
vision of
of a potter making herself into a buddha
it's kind of a nice idea right
[Music]
where he talks about who gave
yeah nice 50.
make 50 that's it
now
[Laughter]
give the thing
[Music]
like tubtin is a common tibetan name it
means the teachings of the able ones
okay um
[Music]
spiritual silence to keep spiritual
silence
which we didn't keep at all
i guess it was the time it was
coming out of virus times and we all
want to talk to each other
so anyway muni means
[Music]
and dry is a doer okay so
it's rain rain rain
sender rain center
is indra so but it means lord of the
gods
number one god so moonendra
uh to in is the name
in his
[Music]
lord of the able ones and then
who gave birth to them
and then who gave birth to the body
[Music]
too long
sometime in the next few months or
something
[Music]
now he wants to talk about oh by the way
what are those opening lines
we gotta say okay
[Music]
bow down to
commitment to somber
[Music]
with praising somebody
if you want to get
this to technical their goal good
that's part of it yeah it's called the
four
connections right
do you remember get known
[Music]
okay if you study the subject matter you
learn
emptiness and that gets you to
buddhahood and that's the fourth
requirement of a buddhist book
the three parts should be connected okay
don't worry it's called
[Music]
um
okay that's where it comes from and it's
important to get to the next part okay
here we go
so in the praise he doesn't say
buddhas give birth to listeners
it happens
[Music]
come from
he calls them lords of the able one
which in sanskrit is
okay good all right
okay baby
[Music]
why don't they just call them the able
ones or the munis or the silent ones
okay why do they call them the kings of
the silent ones
they have mastered
a king of teachings so we call them
kings
teachings
like
[Music]
and when these
bodhisattvas and self made buddhas and
listeners
[Music]
government
it's not that they push people around
and tax them
the kingdoms of the king they are the
kings of the kingdom of the dharma
teachings
got it
[Music]
we have a picture here this is a very
clever picture
light bulbs
he's a master he's the lord of the able
ones
who who else could juggle enlightenments
how many enlightenments three
[Music]
then it's from these kings of the dharma
by the way you can't say it in english
but the verb is different they use the
verb
which is reserved for kings and
buddhists
[Music]
from
okay cool all right
hey how does this birth go like they go
to the hospital and they go to the
maternity
world and you know how's that syndrome
[Music]
these listeners and half buddhists god
took their holy birth from
full burdens kings of kings of
able ones right how does that work
[Music]
the full buddha has to come to your
planet
they have to visit your planet
[Music]
number one the full buddha comes to your
planet
okay uh number two look for
then
[Music]
they come to the planet and they get
there
this commentary and it will take
[Music]
and people who are attracted to their
self-made
buddhist system
[Music]
uh
good so somehow these lower
spiritual practitioners
[Music]
have gone they have to master that first
and then they master emptiness which is
just means
[Music]
they
three stages of spiritual
growth what are the famous three stages
okay
[Music]
monster's name is to some gumling the
real name
is the okay
[Music]
first
colorado you're like what the heck did i
talk about
and you're like daydreaming
[Music]
i don't know
in the next class today okay we're gonna
take those pictures now
and turn them into an experience
don't forget i said six things are
happening
when we want to have a baby
[Music]
um
foreign
that's number six okay it works
they reached the goals that they were
attracted to
which were not
interplanetary okay
they just wanted to develop themselves
[Music]
um
leading to a sixth step which is the
result number six
is the result of the first five that's
an important part
the sixth the seven part body to the
instructions where
six causes and one result
[Music]
foreign
and we have a silly picture
which doesn't have much meaning at all
[Music]
now
if you really got the same thing
um
[Music]
but if you wanna if after the program
i have chosen all the main ideas okay
[Music]
then you can say you're ready to go to
the next stage of the pack okay
um
[Music]
you know he's like anticipating
your questions he builds a question in
your mind
and then he says hey were you wondering
why
and you're like yes
um
okay so here's the question okay
look many listeners are cheating
[Music]
um
it's so common for the
the self-made guys to lag behind by one
line
why is it more common
what's the evidence that they are often
laggers because
how much 300 yay
it's like i don't know i was studying
this last night i was like
duh duh
[Music]
now the question makes sense right i'll
say the question again
[Music]
okay
listeners get the teaching on dependent
origination
why because they're self-made
retards oops that's probably really bad
karma
okay they're always stuck behind so the
other guy says
why is that you know aren't they
[Music]
that they say
it's wrong to say they were born from
the buddhists
because there was such a tragic delay
how can you say they're born from the
buddhists
oh yeah
[Music]
you know their head has to get flattened
out
you know what why are you saying they
got born from the buddhists they had to
go through another
some sorry birth they had to go through
a very painful birth again
why are you calling them so cool
[Music]
they do get teachings on
the wheel of life the 12 links okay
[Music]
and not start understanding emptiness
okay
so it says look they got great teachings
on
the twelve links certainly how that
you already learned some emptiness
three hundred dollars you ready
there's only two english cognates for
dershta there's only two english words
that i know of there's probably more
they'd come from
durstah okay one
is the name of a famous mountain range
you're looking for anything that has a
dura sound in it
[Music]
huh 300.
okay
we have a mountain range near here where
i did my three-year retreat
which is called the dragoons dragoon
comes from a soldier who wears a red
outfit
that was supposed to suggest a dragon
so dragon and dragoon are the only two
words in english that i know of there's
probably more
that come from the same root as
dirsh okay
and the real root is dirk okay
now why is a dragon called drag
uh evil eye they traditionally had an
evil eye if you looked into a dragon's
eye
you would turn to stone um uh
jumping
that's uh no sorry
this dershta means seen in this lifetime
a karmic result which is seen in this
lifetime
is called
um
us negative right like atheist or
apolitical or apathetic okay
it's not seen in this lifetime it's seen
in the next lifetime so
i'm gonna
amanda
[Music]
nirvana for the self-made guys is not
um
[Music]
in
there's a great hotel uh in
uh what's
[Music]
for 300 dollars you can go to the
dragons at bisbee
[Music]
okay
appreciate
[Music]
a tree which
regrows itself after a long period of
time
[Music]
you
unavoidable seed at the center of the
trunk
which grew again in the next life okay
keep getting
it's incredible what happens to your
brain is nice
it's but it's it's like now
maybe they don't miss nirvana in this
life
[Music]
they got what they wanted okay
explain there's an irony in saying
they got what they wanted
[Music]
okay and and to say they got what they
wanted
for them is always a two-step
process meaning this life and next life
okay
um
but
yeah the only thing you can say about
all your day was
oh he was already in a gorgeous didn't
okay
yeah he's the one who gave up his eye
because he was frustrated oh then he got
frustrated okay
anyway his most famous book is called
the 400 verses
okay who's nagarjuna's teacher
[Music]
noise
okay uh
if you understand emptiness
well nobody you didn't comfortable
reach nirvana in that life
certain to be experienced in your next
life okay
self-made buddhist can happen all right
next picture i think well we can get
deep
so i'd i'd like to talk about something
okay we have time
[Music]
um
okay and what's that you meet your
teachers
young uh okay but you
who knows what they're talking about
from birth
from childhood you meet them age five
age six
okay
give someone
but the point is of the cool thing
about being a reincarnated native llama
is that after you die and you get to the
bottom and you come into this life you
know screaming and pooping
you have a teacher waiting there for you
it's so cool i mean people don't talk
about it
but imagine what it's like
try to imagine what it is
[Music]
like
and of all the karmas in the universe
the karma to meet a really great teacher
is extremely rare
extremely rare so here you are you know
you're born
on the other side of the fallopian tube
there's going to be
some people waiting for you
okay
those dudes are waiting for me to pick
me up
to pick up where i left off in this life
um
the wisdom of a self-made buddha
[Music]
uh the book he just quoted is
the middleweight
[Music]
it's a nickname for negotiating
and sometimes among people who know
it's called middleweight i just read
middleweight you're like what i don't
think it is
so zoomed out or the
two retreats from now we're going to go
deep into
[Music]
to study stuff that you is hopeless
in buddhism it's a tradition
to study things that there's no way
you're going to understand it
because
you know i used to do rowing
they would say run up and down the
stadium 20 times
you know in the winter because the ice
was covering the
lake we couldn't road so you say go out
and run up and down the
[Music]
um
to push yourself spiritually is
really cool okay it's like yoga because
sometimes you just push yourself
[Music]
um
yeah there you go i just love this
picture
a lady uh taking her some
deep book i'm thinking of that book you
guys gave to brother
she treasures that like unbelievable
and uh she she's like that all the time
she has it in her hand all the time
every morning and uh so if you see her
all right so
first of all there'll be people waiting
for you right
and then secondly uh the books will be
waiting for you
okay the wisdom will be waiting for you
okay so that's another reason why
i i really encourage you to try to see
emptiness directly
okay
[Music]
give
waiting for you personally
[Music]
and i know who's waiting for me and i
know what's waiting for me okay
we're having trouble getting these guys
online yeah
uh thanks for the amazing teachings i've
had many aha moments
but there's still something going on in
my mind
how is it that buddhas actually help us
i'm trying to develop the idea of
bodhichitta in my own heart
but i'm struggling a lot because i
intellectualize everything
i become a real bodhisattva and then a
buddha
who are all of these countless beings
that i'm helping
okay how concretely how do i teach them
and then how do i receive those
teachings from them
okay cool cool and
[Music]
much of it is intellectual and and it's
not a bad thing
okay it's kind of like einstein on
steroids
okay it's like the goal
is to be uh super
intelligent because then you can help
more people
a super intelligent
[Music]
christ love in his heart or something
imagine
somebody who's a combination you know
a physician who is technically
skilled excellent at what they do
physically dexterous to sew up your
operation
so it's not a bad thing
in fact it's the goal in buddhism
that you will become super intelligent
like
much beyond einstein
[Music]
that's a good thing and there's some
kind of prejudice against that nowadays
i don't know in some countries or in
some
communities you know you should move
like
yeah hello in
in this tradition it's not possible okay
the more you think the better
uh the more uh right
[Music]
highly here you want a surgeon
working on your heart who has thought
about how to do it
okay seriously and uh
and you want them to have love okay but
[Music]
in the diamond way
everybody everybody you meet
is teaching you your karma gets so
powerful
[Music]
how we drive back to tucson from so
diamond mountain's in the middle of
nowhere
and if you drive to the next big city
there's also nothing between here and
there like you're trying to get a good
meal
forget
[Music]
and they'll show you the monster i never
wanted to spend the three dollars
i i think you also have to swear not to
tell anybody
what he looks like if you pay your three
dollars so
i don't know i never paid the three
dollars okay
uh and i'm not asking okay i don't want
to break the faith
uh but uh
the people you meet at the monster is a
is a weird thing
i have stopped at the burger king at the
monster
uh i have because i was hungry and
uh i said i'll take
they said they are advertising a veggie
burger
and i'm like you guys got veggie burgers
they're like yeah we got veggie burgers
i'll take one god i didn't know you guys
out in the middle of nowhere in cattle
country
you're selling a veggie burger and the
guy said yeah we got veggie burgers
and he he unwrapped the hamburger
and he took out the meat and he
re-wrapped it and handed it to me and
charged me more than the hamburger
and so the kind of people you meet in
those places
you know who came to see the monster for
three dollars
you're like oh you know must be some
poor uneducated person right you think
that you really do think that i know
it's prejudice but you think that
and uh what i'm saying is
[Music]
you know so yeah that is
see you in 10 minutes right see you guys
in 10 minutes
i